So now that we understand how services work,
let's review how Android determines your app's priority. App
priority is divided into three general buckets. Critical,
high, and low. Within each bucket the apps are
prioritized in a queue. With the app that's
been at the lowest priority for the longest, the
first to be executed. Critical apps are those that
are active. They're in the foreground, interacting with users.
That includes activities in the foreground and apps
running foreground services. High priority apps, include any visible
activities and any application with a running service.
While less impactful than killing a foreground app, destroying
visible activities or cancelling services running tasks like
background updates it's still going to be noticeable to users.
So, the system will only kill them in
an extreme resource crunch. Apps in the background though,
they're the red shirted ensigns of the app priority
landing party. Any background app will be killed as
needed, in a last seen, first killed order, in
order to help support the higher priority apps. I like
to think of this as the three laws of
Android resource management. Law one, Android will keep all apps
that interact with the user running smoothly. Android will
keep all apps with visible activities or running services running.
Unless doing so violates the first law. And third, Android will keep all
apps in the background running, unless this
violates the first or second laws. So
with all of that in mind, consider these four apps. What do you
think is the priority order of each of these apps, according to the system.